我们现在要谈谈雅可比矩阵的形状。机器人操纵器有
We're going to talk now about the shape of the Jacobian matrix. A robot manipulator has
一般有N个关节，N可能是一个小数，机器人可能只有两个
in general got N joints, N could be a small number, the robot might have only two
关节。机器人可能有100个关节。我想知道什么是影响
joints. The robots might have 100 joints. I want to understand what's the effect of
机器人操纵器雅可比矩阵的形状上的关节数量，因为雅可比矩阵
the number of joints on the shape of the robot manipulator Jacobian matrix, because the Jacobian
每个关节有一列。因此，N关节机器人具有N列的操纵器雅可比矩阵。
has one column per joint. So, an N joint robot has a manipulator Jacobian matrix with N columns.
雅可比行列式对于空间速度矢量的每个元素具有一行。所以，对于动议
The Jacobian has one row for each element of the spatial velocity vector. So, for motion
在三维空间中，空间速度矢量有6个元素-3个用于平移
in three dimensions, the spatial velocity vector has got 6 elements – 3 for translational
速度和角速度为3。而且，这意味着雅可比矩阵总是具有
velocity and 3 for angular velocity. And, that means the Jacobian matrix always has
六排。因此，机器人操纵器雅可比矩阵是6×N矩阵。
six rows. So, the robot manipulator Jacobian matrix is a 6 x N matrix.
这个机器人只有4个关节，我们将其称为欠驱动机器人。而且，这意味着
This robot only has 4 joints and we call it an under actuated robot. And, that means that
它的任务空间不包括所有的SE3集。虽然末端执行器可以实现
its task space doesn't cover all of the set SE3. Although the end effector can achieve
在其工作空间范围内的所有位置，它无法实现所有可能的方向。
all positions within the limits of its works space, it's not able to achieve all possible orientations.
因此，例如，当机器人在这样的配置中，它可以调整方向
So, for example, when the robot in a configuration like this, it can adjust the orientation of
这样的抓手。但是，它不可能调整夹具的方向
the gripper like that. But, it's impossible for it to adjust the orientation of the gripper
在那个方向或那个方向。
in that direction or in that direction.
让我们考虑只有4个关节的机器人的情况。这通常被称为
Let's consider the case of a robot with only 4 joints. This is often referred to as an
欠驱动机器人系统。在这种情况下，机器人Jacobian有6行4列。
under-actuated robotic system. In this case, the robot Jacobian has got 6 rows and 4 columns.
雅可比不是方形的，因此，我们不能反转它。但这不一定
The Jacobian is not square, and therefore, we cannot invert it. But that's not necessarily
一个问题。像这样的机器人无法围绕x轴或y轴旋转工具。它的
a problem. A robot like this is unable to rotate the tool about the x or y axis. It's
只是它的构造方式。它不能以这种方式旋转工具。所以，我们可以罢工
just the way it's constructed. It cannot rotate the tool in that way. So, we can strike out
这些元素是机器人的空间速度。因为我们无法控制这些周围的速度
these elements of the robot’s spatial velocity. Since we can't control velocity around these
轴，让我们删除它们。
axes, let's just remove them.
如果我这样做，那么我也应该删除雅可比矩阵中的相应行。
If I do that, then I should also remove the corresponding rows in the Jacobian matrix.
而且，结果现在是一个4x4系统。现在，雅可比矩阵是可逆的。特定
And, the result now is a 4 x 4 system. And now, the Jacobian matrix is invertible. Given
在期望的空间速度，现在是更小的空间速度矢量。我们可以计算
a desired spatial velocity, it's a smaller spatial velocity vector now. We can compute
机器人关节角速度。我们需要获得那个空间速度。
the robot joint angle velocities. We need to obtain that spatial velocity.
这是一个可能有100个关节的机器人。在这种情况下，操纵器雅可比是
Here's a robot that has perhaps 100 joints. In this case, the manipulator Jacobian is
一个6x100矩阵。它不是正方形，我们无法反转它。我们可以计算一些东西
a 6 x 100 matrix. It's not square and we cannot invert it. We can compute something
称为伪逆，并且通常用符号加表示。
called the pseudo-inverse and that's often denoted by the symbol plus.
以这种方式计算伪逆。直到你，这看起来很直接
The pseudo-inverse is computed in this way. This looks quite straight forward until you
提醒自己，这里的术语实际上是100x100矩阵，我们需要
remind yourself that the term inside here is in fact a 100 x 100 matrix and we need to
反过来。从计算上讲，这不是一件简单的事情。但是，如果我们使用这个
invert that. And computationally, that's not a simple thing to do. However, if we use this
伪逆，我们可以写出一个与所需空间速度相关的表达式
pseudo-inverse, we can write an expression that relates the desired spatial velocity
机器人末端执行器对其100个关节中每个关节的所需速度。
of the robots end effector to the required velocity of each of its 100 joints.
但是对于像这样的机器人来说，我们可以做更多的事情-一个拥有更多机器人的机器人
But we can do an extra thing as well in the case of a robot like this – a robot with more
超过6个关节。我们可以在这里添加这个术语，我们将其称为零空间运动。
than 6 joints. We can add this term here and we refer to this as the null-space motion.
它在这里预先乘以这个矩阵表达式，有效地过滤它，所以
It's pre-multiplied by this matrix expression here, which effectively filters it, so that
此动作不会影响机器人末端执行器的姿势。我们可以使用这个动议，
this motion does not affect the pose of the robot end effector. We can use this motion,
这不影响末端效应器的姿势来做一些改变形状的东西
which doesn't affect the end effector pose to do things like change the shape of the
臂。我们也可以用它来做一些事情，比如将机器人关节从其极限移开
arm. We can also use it to do things like move a robot joint away from its limit towards
其工作范围的中间部分。
the middle part of its working range.
因此，我们使用这种额外的关节速度运动来改变手臂的形状，移动关节
So, we use this extra joint velocity motion to change the shape of the arm, move joints
远离他们的极限。同时不影响末端效应器的姿势。这很漂亮
away from their limits. At the same time not affecting the end effector pose. It's a pretty
整洁的把戏。该矩阵N被称为雅可比矩阵的零空间。它
neat trick. This matrix N is referred to as the null space of the Jacobian matrix. It
是由机械手雅可比矩阵预乘的矢量集，给出一个
is the set of vectors that pre-multiplied by the manipulator Jacobian matrix, give a
结果为零。在这种特殊情况下，如果机器人有100个关节，那么零空间
result of zero. In this particular case, if the robot had 100 joints, then the null space
将是尺寸94.那是100减6.因此，N将是6×94元素矩阵。
would be of dimension 94. That's 100 minus 6. So, N would be a 6 x 94 element matrix.
我将导入一个以3D方式移动的冗余机器人模型，这就是模型
I'm going to import the model of a redundant robot that moves in 3D and that's the model
超3D。并且，我将要求一个有20个关节的机器人。举例来说，
hyper 3D. And, I'm going to ask for a robot with 20 joints. To illustrate, for example,
我需要选择一组关节角度。我需要选择20个数字。我知道如果
I need to choose a set of joint angles. I need to choose 20 numbers. I know that if
它们都等于零，机器人将处于奇点。
they're all equal to zero, the robot will be at a singularity.
所以，我要做的是选择20个随机数。我将使用内置的MATLAB
So, what I'm going to do is to choose 20 random numbers. I'm going to use the MATLAB built-in
功能兰特。所以，这是我的关节角度向量-范围内的20个随机数
function rand. So, this is my joint angle vector – 20 random numbers in the range
0到1.并且，我可以为机器人绘制这个特定的关节角度配置，这是
0 to 1. And, I can plot this particular joint angle configuration for a robot and this is
它看起来像什么。如果我可以稍微浏览一下，我们可以看到它
what it looks like. If I can just have a bit of a look around and we can see that it's
指向略微向上，它有一些弯曲和扭曲。
pointing slightly upwards and it's got a few bends and twists in it.
现在我有一组关节角度，我有一个机器人模型，我可以计算一个雅可比行列式
Now that I have the set of joint angles and I have a robot model, I can compute a Jacobian
矩阵。而且，我们已经看到了如何为许多其他类型的机器人做到这一点。我使用了雅可比
matrix. And, we've seen how to do that for many other types of robots. I used the Jacobian
方法和我传递一组关节角度。而且，这是雅可比矩阵。我们可以看到
method and I pass in the set of joint angles. And, this is the Jacobian matrix. We can see
它有6行，它有20列，因为有20个关节。
that it's got 6 rows and it's got 20 columns because there are 20 joints.
如果我试图反转这个矩阵，我会得到一个错误，因为矩阵不是
If I tried to invert this matrix, I'm going to get an error because the matrix is not
广场。MATLAB告诉我，我不能这样做，但我可以计算伪逆。和，
square. MATLAB is telling me I can't do that but I can compute the pseudo-inverse. And,
这是使用MATLAB内置函数pinv计算的，并传入雅可比矩阵。
that's computed using the MATLAB built-in function pinv, and pass in the Jacobian matrix.
而且，这是伪逆的结果。而且，我们可以看到我们在工作区中
And, this is the result of the pseudo-inverse. And, we can see that we have here in the workspace
现在是一个20x6矩阵，雅可比矩阵的伪逆。
now a 20 x 6 matrix, the pseudo-inverse of the Jacobian matrix.
现在，我们讨论了零空间运动。并且，为了计算零空间运动，
Now, we talked about the null space motion. And, in order to compute the null space motion,
我们需要计算雅可比矩阵本身的零空间，MATLAB具有这样做的功能。
we need to compute the null space of the Jacobian matrix itself and MATLAB has the function to do that.
它是函数null并且我传入雅可比矩阵，这里是零空间矩阵。
It's the function null and I pass in the Jacobian matrix and here is the null space matrix.
零空间矩阵有20行，只有14列。14来自20，这是
The null space matrix has 20 rows and only 14 columns. 14 comes from 20, which is the
原雅可比列中的列数减去6.而6是该原始的等级
number of columns in the original Jacobian minus 6. And 6 is the rank of that original
雅可比。这是雅可比矩阵中唯一列的数量。所以，有6个独特的
Jacobian. That's the number of unique columns in the Jacobian matrix. So, there were 6 unique
列，雅各比派的零空间中存在14列。14加
columns and there were 14 columns that exist in the null space of that Jacobian. 14 plus
6等于20，原始列数。
6 equals 20, the original number of columns.
让我们总结一下机器人雅可比矩阵可以具有的一些不同形状。对于
Let's summarize some of the different shapes that a robot Jacobian matrix can have. For
在一个带有6个关节的机器人的情况下，我们说机器人是完全启动的。雅可比人
the case of a robot with 6 joints, we say that the robot is fully actuated. The Jacobian
将是一个方形的6x6矩阵。并且具有6个关节的机器人能够完全访问所有
will be a square 6 x 6 matrix. And a robot with 6 joints is able to fully access all
在SE3内构成。这意味着，任何位置和任意
poses within SE3. That means, any position and any arbitrary
取向。对于少于6个关节的机器人的情况，我们称之为
orientation. For the case of a robot with less than 6 joints, which we refer to as an
欠驱动机器人，雅可比行星将是一个6xN矩阵。它将拥有比列数更多的行。
under-actuated robot, the Jacobian will be a 6 x N matrix. It will have more rows than it has columns.
这意味着机器人无法访问SE3中的所有可能姿势。并且，按顺序
This means that the robot cannot access all possible poses within a SE3. And, in order
为了控制目的而使用雅可比行列式，我们需要将它放在一边，我们就是这样做的
to use the Jacobian for control purposes, we need to square it up and we do that by
去除一些空间自由度。我们消除雅可比矩阵中的一些行
removing some spatial degrees of freedom. We eliminate some rows in the Jacobian matrix
这样它就变成了一个5x5或4x4雅可比矩阵，然后是可逆的。在这种情况下
so that it becomes a 5 x 5 or 4 x 4 Jacobian matrix which is then invertible. In the case
一个超过6个关节的机器人，我们称之为过度驱动的机器人
of a robot with more than 6 joints, which we refer to as an over actuated robot, the
雅可比矩阵的列数多于行数。它是一个6xN矩阵。
Jacobian matrix has more columns than it has rows. It's a 6 x N matrix.
为了使用雅可比矩阵进行控制，我们采用伪逆。该
In order to use the Jacobian matrix for control purposes, we take its pseudo-inverse. The
像这样的机器人的巨大优势是我们可以考虑有备用关节和
great advantage of a robot like this is that we can think about having spare joints and
我们可以使用其中一些备用关节来做我们称之为零空间运动的事情。而且，虽然
we can use some of these spare joints to do what we call null space motion. And, while
我们保持无效的姿势不变，我们可以调整所有的关节来改变
we hold the ineffective pose constant, we can adjust all of the joints to change the
手臂的形状或移动关节远离运动限制。
shape of the arm or move the joints away from motion limits.